[Music]
this is software engineering radio the
podcast for professional developers on
the web at se-radio.net
sc radio is brought to you by the ieee
computer society by ieee software
magazine online at computer.org software
welcome to software engineering radio
i'm your host gavin henry and today my
guest is daniel stemberg
daniel is the founder and lead developer
of curl and lib curl an internet
protocol geek an open source person and
a developer
he has worked on http implementations
for over 25 years he's been active in
the ietf for over a decade and worked on
the http stack in firefox for several
years at mozilla he currently works at
wolf ssl
robert welcome to software engineering
radio is there anything i miss in your
bio that you'd like to add
thank you and good to be here now i
think that sort of covers the basics
but possibly i could add i've done a lot
of other open source stuff as well but
sort of curl is my baby that's my
primary focus
excellent and this show is going to be
quite different for me and for the
podcast in general
we're going to be talking about the curl
project
history war stories
loads of different things so it's going
to be really exciting
we're going to have a chat about five or
six topics related to the curb project
for around 10 minutes each so let's
start
daniel please take us through the
25-year journey if 25 years is correct
you can bring me up on that of carl in
10 minutes or so or do your best
go
[Laughter]
well 25 years
it is if we count the projects i did
before i renamed it curl so basically my
journey with curl started
sort of in the mid 90s i worked on
another open source project with a
friend what was it was an irc bot we
called it the dancer at the time
it doesn't really matter but in 1996 or
so in the autumn there i figured out
that i wanted to provide a currency
translation or exchange service for the
bot for ioc users so i started to look
around on how to do that and i realized
that of course if you want to do a
currency exchange we need the currency
rates sort of reasonably updated every
now and then so i needed a little tool
to download currency rates using http
because i found sites that hosted
currency rates on http
so i looked around and i found a little
tool called http get that would do the
job for me
and so i started working with that tool
to do my currency exchange thing and
then i pretty
immediately found some issues with that
tool so i corrected those and i sent
patches back to the author who
accepted it and then released for web
releases for that tool http get and that
first http get version that i found and
used was released in november 1996
and
i think raphael the author of that tool
he got bored with me pretty quickly
because i kept sending him patches for
doing more things so i became the
maintainer of that tool
pre
within weeks actually i think i don't
remember exactly the timing there but i
was the maintainer of that tool
within a few releases so i think it did
my first release of that tool in the end
of 1996.
so that is 25 years a little bit more
than that so i worked on that tool http
get for a while
until i realized i wanted to extend my
currency exchange service with more
rates and i found another site
that hosted currency rates on gopher so
yay i need more currency rates so i just
need to make my tool support gopher as
well so that i could download go for two
http and gopher so i added go for
support to http get and then http get
became a pretty bad name because it
didn't only do http so it did http and
gopher so i just changed name to url get
instead because it would get urls and
then by that time the tool would also
work on urls that was one of the early
changes i participated to make in the
tool and then
we kept it as url get for a while we we
released version
two and version three and called it
urlgate during 1997 and then and i also
found i don't remember exactly why i
think i found another site as well that
provided currency rates over ftp so i
added ftp support so now it could
download data from ftp gopher and ftp
and in the early 1998
i started to add support for ftp uploads
as well
and then again i realized that wow
calling it url get it doesn't reflect
the nature of the tools is now it
doesn't only do gets anymore it would do
puts or uploads as well so
i wanted to rename it again
so i renamed it to curl and we released
the first curl version in in march 1998
and i kept the version numbering from
the previous tool so
url get version 3 became curl version
4.0 there in march 1998
so then it could download from three
protocols upload to one protocol and
there's the c
in carol for c programming language no i
actually i've wanted to have a name and
i thought i would be fun with the name
that has url in it because it works on
urls
so i and then i figured i wanted short
maybe a pronounceable name you know
unique style so maybe c could be
for client i figured client for urls and
c could also work as a sort of if you
pronounce it see the url
as a sort of more of a puns like thing
so i figured why not and i just want the
primary goal was there to have a short
short word so that you could type it
easily on in command lines so i went
with carl i didn't really
spend a lot of time
with the name it was just yeah let's go
with carl
and it's stuck and i think it's a pretty
good name
so at that time then
in 1998 by that time it started in 1996
it was slightly less than 300 lines of
code in the first tool i don't have
the entire early history preserved some
sort of restored some of it but the time
i did the first curl release it was
about 2 400 lines of code
and i think it had 25 command line
options or so
and that was only a command line tool
then and we started working on that
or i kept on working on that and then we
got people trying out submitting patches
and you know extending it more and more
and the first major change
from that point was in the summer 2000
summer here in in my parts of the world
i
re-modeled the internals a little bit
and provided a library so lib curl was
born in in 2000
so that we could provide
well an api and internet transfer
capabilities basically to others other
applications or programming languages
and so on
because i thought about it from the
beginning and i thought it would be cool
and at that time i sort of made it
happen and when i did
one of the first that immediately
adopted libcurl as a library was the php
language which i think was fortunate for
us because they really had a lot of
users they still have a lot of users so
they really
tested it they really got to submit a
lot of bugs and they had ideas how to do
it and so we got it tested and it took
off
really quickly from that point well not
like a rocket but it sort of gradually
increased popularity and people started
to use it and
from that point we just kept on fixing
bugs adding things we added more
protocol support over time we added tls
support already before we had the
library so it supported hps already back
in
i believe 1999
and
from that point on we've
just kept on
adding support for things features
and a lot of different
backends we pretty soon decided to
support multiple
implementations for different protocols
so for example we started with tls
support with the old ss i don't even
know how they pronounce it you know the
precursor to openssl ssli or whatever
they pronounce it and then we switch to
openssl but pretty soon we also started
to support other tls libraries like gnu
tls and
nss and a few of the others and over
time we've always worked on supporting a
lot of different tls libraries and over
time then we also have added support for
multiple different libraries for other
things like ssh or idn and
name resolving and stuff like that
so we had that sort of infrastructure
idea from early on
to pretty much allow the user who is
building curl to decide what kind of
third-party libraries they want to use
when they build curl thanks yeah i've
seen the options when you go to install
lib curl or curl it gives you
different versions of tls libraries you
know if you're installing through a
debian packet manager or ubuntu or
something
thanks and nothing a good potted history
best you can do in 10 minutes were you
quite an accomplished seek programmer
before you started in 96 just before i
finish off this section move us on yes i
had been working
i mean i am a software developer since
of course it's before that so i had been
working professionally with c
programming for
several years before that so i was
pretty comfortable with writing program
cc yes
excellent so now we've had that good
history lesson
can you think of a couple of things for
the next 10 minutes that you learned
over that time
that surprised you or might surprise
others
in those 25 years
i'm not sure i have learned much
sort of big surprises
i think i learned all those things that
most people would learn
doing something like this for a long
time for example just learning how to
write something that is actually
maintainable over time for example
clear code
comments in the code explaining things
to my future self and stuff like that
and
the value of doing test cases and
documenting things and
just having sensible hygiene in the
project nothing of that is surprising or
strange in any way but it's
when you work in something for a long
time i think more of those things
actually
become important because
you get to sort of
discover things about your own code and
thinking down the road because you have
to
when you live with it for such a long
time
maybe
what about a protocol that you
implemented that took much longer than
you ever expected and that surprised you
oh yeah but but i think in general i
mean hp is my primary product i think
that's the protocol
curl is most known for most used for and
the one i spent most time on and i think
http is one of those protocols that yeah
it seems so simple
i remember when i started working on
http that was so simple to implement you
know just text and you just type get and
it'll get that
and over time you you really realize
that http is
yes it seems so easy on the outside and
sort of on the surface when you see that
text and and of course over the years
and recent 10 years we've switched away
from the text based as well but it was
never an easy protocol and it's
getting more and more complicated over
over time so implementing something http
today it's really really complicated in
particular if you want to support
multiple versions
so yeah i think basically all protocols
that are well used have turned out to be
much more complicated in the real
life and in real world than i for sure
sort of foresee from the beginning
and i mean
none of them are ever done right because
we keep getting bug reports
today on stuff we wrote and implemented
decades ago that things are never done
it's doing things
internet protocols networking across the
internet is challenging and have you
been surprised on
protocols that have come and gone or
libraries that you use or things you've
implemented that
have outlasted how long you think you'd
need to support them or you've had to
drop stuff over that time my primary
view of things is that i don't really
foresee i don't make any projections or
or try to tell how the world would look
in the future i'm looking at where we
are right now and i'm trying to adapt to
that and maybe where we're going this
year or this
few months ahead so i never try to
actually tell what we will do in the
next two five ten years that because i
find it impossible to do that
but sure in general things stick around
much longer than you ever think when it
shows up
so of course
for example introducing new protocol
versions something you we know that the
old protocol versions they will stick
around
for a very very long time even when
something new better shinier comes along
and in curl we have this concept that we
don't modify we don't break apis or api
so we stick around we support everything
we provided in the past as well so i'm
not sure i'm surprised
that it's more of how the world works
and of course
it's really hard to say especially when
you use a lot of third-party libraries
it's hard to say sure we can add support
for a new third-party library today but
we can't tell how that's third-party
library will be maintained survive or
act tomorrow right or in two years or
five years or 12 years who knows where
they are going so over the years of
course we realized that
some for example tls libraries that we
added support for in the past they
mostly maybe died over the years and
then we
eventually rip out support for that
particular library or subsystem or stuff
like that
and the infamous question that i'm sure
people always ask is are you happy of
the choice of the c programming
languages uh language for
carol and lib curl
in general i would say that i'm very
happy and that is based on several
things really because first of all we
started as i mentioned before we started
this in the
90s and in the 90s making a portable
library or portable tool portable
anything there was no
real choice other than c to go with i
mean c plus plus could possibly have
been a choice but not even c plus plus
had a stable api back in the day so you
couldn't really do any portable
libraries back then with c plus plus and
i've never been a c plus plus fan so i'm
i
i avoid c plus plus so yes i'm happy
with c and c has then made it possible
to really really make curl and lip curl
the portable
available everywhere library that it is
it is c that is the explanation why it
is used and can be used in so many many
different places operating systems cpu
architectures and everything
and i would say it isn't until
very recent years that they actually
have started to appear viable
alternatives that could have been used
but
they can be used now they could not be
used 20 years ago one of the benefits
and one of the things with curl is that
we have the age we have the maturity we
have been around for so long so it has
had the time to mature and you know
stabilize and everything and that's a
very big thing too
yeah it's not something you just want to
start again and a new language that's
come up
no exactly because whatever you do it
takes a really long time to become a
really stable and solid thing to do
like this and i i think that's one of
the primary benefits you have when you
go with curl that you get all this
battle proven
time and
have been shaped by nature for so long
and it's that's hard to replicate or i
mean you can't replicate it it'll just
take a long time
well that brings us nicely on to my next
section
which i've called
key events in the timeline
so i really like the history and
timeline document that you have on
github and i saw on the mail nest
it's very complete could you pick two or
three of your favorite things from the
timeline filed
you shared i think it was
december or last month
or maybe talk about things you wish you
could delete on that list
[Laughter]
well there's so much well i've got a
couple in my list then you can
agree or disagree so i'm thinking when
curl was on mars
when apple included it in mac os
your favorite protocols when the user
base reached a certain amount the number
of bugs when you got your first
cve security thing
any of those yeah there's a good events
so of course in the beginning when carl
started of course you know as anything
that is started as a small project
when people
like it start to use it and adopt it in
different surroundings that those are
key events and those were really fun to
mark so of course when apple included it
in in mac os in 2001
in september 2001 that was really a key
event for me because it's so that was
one of the first
non-linux operating systems that
actually adopted curl as a standard tool
in their operating system so that marked
something
sort of a notch and a sign of success so
i have that marked and i thought that
was a really great moment in time
and of course as you mentioned it was
confirmed to be used in the mars
helicopter mission in 2021 and that was
a really fun moment of course a really
excellent ego boost and one of the
things we've talked back and forth in
the code project for for a long time is
to get any kind of confirmation that
curl has been used in space because
we've had that people have mentioned
that in the past that it might have been
used on the iss and stuff like that but
i've never had it confirmed from anyone
or had any proof and then finally when
we got the proof that they actually used
it on in the mars mission that was such
a cool moment to
say that yes
finally one more planet than just earth
so is that in
something that was doing requests within
an operating system on mars or coming
back to the base they won't tell so it's
really impossible to say i have no idea
they've just said that they've used it
in the helicopter mission i wonder what
the latency is
yeah i imagine it can't really be done
from mars to earth using curl i would
imagine it must be something
shorter distance but i really couldn't
tell
and they won't tell so
we can just speculate on whatever it is
for me of course one key moment in time
is when i got the pole hem award prize
in sweden in 2017 so i actually got a
gold medal from a which is an
engineering award here in sweden it's a
really old one is over 100 years old
sort of handed out to
engineers in sweden who have sort of
accomplished something
blah blah but it was a good moment in
time for me
and i got that award handed over to me
by the swedish king at a great gala
dinner here in stockholm
that was awesome wow congratulations and
the user-based figures or bugs or
security issues or was there a point on
that timeline where you thought what
have i created you know
there have been some times you know when
people have
said something that have made me realize
that wow the number of users is a really
high number now i remember counting at
some point in time when i i realized it
might be several hundred million
installations now that's crazy
and nowadays we count somewhere maybe
more than 10 billion installations so
you get a little to the numbers because
they're so immensely big now so it's
it's hard to even imagine but of course
i remember stuff like when when i
realized that it was used in for example
wow it's installed in most
android installations and i when i also
realized that it's used by default ios
then i also realized that wow this is
used in quite a lot of places
and i have these
fun email interactions when i got that
email from from a woman i think this was
in 2016 or so i got an email from a
woman who well she was confused but she
wanted my help to fix her instagram
account
because apparently i know the instagram
people because she found my name in
instagram and that was one of the
moments when i realized wow they're
using my code in in the instagram app on
ios as well
those particular moments could be a
little bit of eye-opening that it is
used in
a lot of those big volume
apps
yeah it's kind of mind-blowing isn't it
when you just think about everything
that document so yeah i noticed that you
keep track of the
security releases as well
are they different things or is that
programming patterns that keep appearing
or how do you classify those types of
things i try to keep
very close track of exactly all the
security problems that we have had
reported on curl and we have this back
boundary that where we reward security
researchers who who file or submit
issues that are confirmed to be security
problems and then i i try to make it a
really good effort i pride myself to
actually go into the details and then
research exactly when we insert the
problem when we fix it and try to figure
out exactly how it happened and how you
can exploit it and everything that and
try to document all of that and part of
the reason for doing that except for
then later being able to do fun graphs
and when bugs were inserted or fixed is
that is also a good way to you know try
to learn something from the problem it
was inserted at this point this is the
mistake
we fix it like this but what could we
have done or what should we do now so
that we don't
do the same kind of that or even exactly
the same mistake once more
that's really hard because
it's like a normal bug right when you
once you read it and once you have that
report you can all you realize that yes
that's a silly mistake why did we ever
do it like that of course it's stupid
but it wasn't stupid or at least we
didn't realize the stupidity at the time
when we inserted it
so what do you learn from that so
it's typically very hard to actually not
view it as a
one-off mistake and sort of everyone
makes mistakes
we can't fix that but then we also try i
have tried to do certain things in the
code like avoiding certain styles of
programming patterns
for example one of the things i realized
actually
that we had
several security problems that were the
result of
silly integral overflows and
reallocks or mallocs based on that
potential
integer overflow and i've actually done
two things in the project to reduce the
likeliness of that ever happening again
is that
one of the things is that we've now
nowadays have a
pretty much universal limit on string
links or string data inputs you can send
to libcro which
limits string size to it i think it's
eight megabytes which is a ridiculously
high limit but
it avoids the chance that someone can
put in a string that is next to two
gigabytes on a 32-bit architecture for
example or stuff like that and we also
have a
introduced a new sort of internal api
and
buffer system to try to make it reduce
the number of real logs done within the
c code because it i
realized that we had several of those
security problems
in close association to reallocks or and
reallocks to growing buffers growing
memory buffers so i'm trying to avoid
stuff like that so
hopefully
avoid some of the mistakes we've done in
the past
other things we're doing that we are
recently or we started
late 2020 so
and i worked with the
isrg who has sponsored a project to
support
replacing the
built-in hp back and the hp coding curl
well not all of it but part of it
with a http library written in rust
called hyper
that's of course another way to
potentially
address or
avoid future mistakes at least see
mistakes by making sure that we use less
c and more other
languages than c
that's a good point to move on to the
next section so war stories i'm calling
this
i'd like you to now talk about some of
the hard bugs you squashed or other
memorable stories during the project's
life if that's okay
what stands out for you and makes you
think if i did that i can do anything
or we could drill into some of those
secure issues a bit more because i like
the sound of what you just explained
what you're doing with the http library
layer so yeah if i did that i can do
anything is there anything that comes up
not really or rather
there's so much of that i think bugging
wise i think
doing things
there are so many layers
of code i think in curl itself there's a
lot of layers and then people
applications and there are languages and
i think in in general we have things
like languages doing bindings doing lib
curl who's doing things so
and then someone writes an application
in that language using the binding using
lib curl who's doing tls doing a
protocol where something is wrong when
you're using a third-party library so i
figure sometimes it's really really
difficult to
understand or
yeah just to figure out where the
problem might be or there's so many
layers so many different
responsibilities so many different
angles it could be
so i think sometimes we really dig
around for a very long time and a lot of
code to figure out where it is so i
think it's common pattern
one of my favorite ones i think i have a
quote somewhere
when facebook reported a problem with
carl
facebook i think they still use they
have a php version and when a lot of
facebook is written in so they use
lib curl from php and well they
experienced some kind of lag that took
i don't remember exactly i think it was
some delay with some milliseconds in
some kind of request and i got it i have
as i said
the response quote because the person i
worked with or communicated with he then
sent me an email and said i tested your
patch in production and it works
and i figured that was fun just because
testing my patch in production on
facebook that seemed like
well it was a few years ago but i was
still hundreds or hundreds of millions
of users and that was fun
another fun little bug i remember
that sort of stands out among other bug
fixes is that
i was contacted by a company in germany
who's doing software for some
car
company
and
the person who contacted me said that we
have eight million cars waiting for a
firmer upgrade here but we can't deliver
that because curl is crashing
okay
and that was back in the day when i
didn't even work on curls so i was just
you but okay thank you for telling me
that but you know curl is a spare time
project here so i don't know what you
expect me to do here because his next
then follow-up question was can you fly
down here tomorrow and help us fix this
i tried to explain to him no i you know
i have this full-time work and you know
i'm expected to live with something this
week and i can't just take off in the
middle of the week go to go to germany
to fix your thing
[Laughter]
i managed to find a friend who could fly
down there and i could help them from
remote so we fixed it within a day or
two so that was fun
but yeah there's been a few of those
adventurous bug fixes over the years
yeah what was the one the other day i
saw on
let me unless and twitter i think it was
to do with the log 4j
xboy wasn't it that's his biggest story
so since
curl
for i don't know exactly why but we
modified the mit license slightly when
we adopted the mit license back in 2001
i think we've switched curl to
materializes so it's slightly modified
from the mit language it's just a few
words that are not the same it's
basically mit but anyway and in that
license file it says copyright blah blah
blah daniel stenberg blah blah blah and
my email address
and that particular license file is
usually included in different operating
systems or products or devices and about
screens
on a lot of places
partly because it's not an mit straight
off so it's usually recognized as their
current license another regular so when
people bundle a lot of licenses it still
stands out because it's not among the
regular mit ones it's separate it's
curled one and it also
usually then ends up as one of the few
licenses that actually has a personal
email address in them so when people
ship products or devices and stuff
and they put together a bunch of
licenses you know hundreds of licenses
isn't
that uncommon
people eventually or some people
eventually find my name and email in
there and they email me about it
about whatever problem they have that is
associated that so they have with their
device or tool or car or printer or
anything computer games is pretty common
too
so people have problems with things they
look around and usually i guess they are
actually pretty upset with something and
they are frantically searching for
someone to contact but i guess in many
cases they already try to contact 22
different people and then finally to
find my email somewhere in there and
then i'm gonna email this guy and he's
gonna help me with my issue whatever the
issue is so i get a lot of
fun emails from people who want help
with issues with their software where i
usually don't even know what they're
talking about
and then
recently i got an email from
a big company they were they're actually
called i didn't say that in the blog
post but they're actually metlife
metlife is a really big insurance
company
and their i think their own fortune 100
and they emailed me a lot of questions
about how to make sure that their
products aren't
vulnerable for the log4j vulnerability
and they called me a partner in the
email i guess they found my my address
in some kind like that scanning a lot of
licenses in their products or something
and of course for me it just turned out
really confusing because
i don't do any java anywhere and i i've
never participated in any java products
anywhere so of course nothing that i
ever wrote has any log4j in it so the
question was mostly confused
but then as i said i've kind of used to
getting those kind of questions because
and i think almost the same day i got
that long for jay question i got another
question from someone who he was upset
about the player choices he got when
playing some soccer game i don't even
remember the name of it but that guy
asked me to help him get better players
and then he sent me also a screenshot
that showed my name in the in the
license window of the computer game
you have to drill pretty deep to get to
the about page in most apps yes
you know
there's some user interface failure if
they're having to go to the about page
and drill into licenses to find a
contact not only user interface failure
i think there's also you know a general
feedback customer relation problem
because i also had a lot of car
problems made to me and finding my name
in a car
infotainment system that is also you
know it takes a lot of will
patience to find it so it says something
about how hard it is for regular people
to actually get in contact with someone
who who did
just the
software for their devices
just before we move on to the next
section it sounded really interesting
what you mentioned about bringing rust
in as a library
will that mean that you've then got
another library
to maintain that as part of the library
or
how will that work
pretty much yes
basically already when you build curl
today or lib curly also we use
third-party libraries for
certain things that we don't do
ourselves like handling tls ssh
different compressions and stuff like
that so we're already leaning on other
libraries for doing part of the
functionality so
when you build lip cartilage ship it
with your
thing you already use lip curl and a
number of other libraries so
when now we're enabling or making it
possible to build lip curl to use
different
rust libraries
you're
only
maybe adding libraries or replacing
libraries so you go with the rust ones
instead of other ones but yes you're
certainly going to
add a dependency and rely on other
libraries as well as on top of leap curl
then so that means the core http
functionality
will be moved away from c and into rust
and as a separate library that way
yes but i'm doing it the same way as i
do with all the different tls libraries
pretty much so i i still have a native
implementation in c that you can replace
at build time so you can go you go
either with a c solution the native one
or you go with the one in hyper the rust
one so at build time you select which
one to go because i'm a firm believer
that i need to
keep and maintain the c version because
as i sort of
talked about
half an hour ago the c version is what
makes carl as portable and as popular in
in so many places so i think the c
version is going to
still stick around and be available and
be used by
i'm not sure if most people but by a lot
of people going forward as well and
we'll see how the rust solutions go i
mean if they will become popular and
used and so on i have really no
way of telling or no idea how they will
fare going forward hopefully they will
be popular and used but i really can't
tell if they will be
yeah going over the timeline of what
the history of carl you know so this is
a long time so you'll just have to see i
suppose
just to close off this section
you mentioned the rust bit to help
potentially with some security issues
to a lot of the security issues
are they particular to
programming parents and c or nothing to
do with c or a combination
or something in how the protocol is
implemented that's been missed i've
tried to count the number of obvious
mistakes that are due to the programming
language c and i think it's about half i
think we're going slightly below half
now but somewhere in the neighborhood of
50 of the problems have been c mistakes
so if we would imagine that the entire
curl would have been written in a memory
safe language maybe we could have
avoided 50 of them but that said we also
do things differently now so i'm not
convinced that we're going to see 50 of
them being seen mistakes in the future
but it's hard to say
excellent thank you so the next section
i'd like to talk about release cycles
and feature request process
can you tell us about your release cycle
the feature request process for example
how do we request features how do you
assess their suitability
and what made me think of this is the
other day
you tweeted about release and the sense
of relief that comes out of that and
then
an hour later a bug report comes in and
you're like
yeah
that's part of the regular release cycle
yes so
i've always been been a believer of the
although traditional
open source mantra to release early and
release often and
nowadays people do that even more since
a lot of software these days or
or server based or cloud-based but
anyway i've always tried to do a lot of
releases so that people can get the
opportunity to have the latest code
often so if we fix anything they don't
have to wait
around for a long time until they get
the next release so
pretty much we started out
early on to do very frequent releases
and after a while maybe a decade i don't
remember exactly when we switched to it
i think it was like 15 years ago or
maybe something like that we switched to
a completely time based release cycle so
we
pretty much just set the clock and we
stick to that cycle so we
we do releases every eight weeks
if nothing
else happens so we stick to that and we
have the first half of that release
cycle open for merging features and
doing changes as we call them things
that are actually
potentially adding features or changing
things and then the second half of that
release cycle we don't accept new
changes or features we just fix bugs
then we do a release and then we start
over
pretty much
i think it has turned out to be pretty
successful
because it limits the speed in which we
allow features and it
also it makes us have a pretty long time
where we only work on bug fixes which
has turned out to be
i think pretty good because it
makes people
work a lot on bug fixes and i think bug
fixes are are the most important things
we can do
and
we stick to this whenever we find
something really critical buggy within
the release cycle
we can make an exception and make
another release without eight weeks
having having sort of
been using that as a cycle and we do
that every now and then when we find
some terrible bugs that we inserted
but the ideal case is eight weeks then
release and usually we don't even
do emergency releases for security fixes
either because
they're rarely that critical so we
usually bundle the security fixes too
and include them in the release at that
particular release
point in time and having eight weeks
like on the clock it makes it also very
easy to plan everything because we know
ahead of time exactly the dates of all
the future releases as long as we just
keep the release cycle we know when we
go to the feature freeze we know when
the release is going to happen
and so on so it's also an easy
scheduling thing
for me i think
and for the relief i think it's when we
work on something for eight weeks and we
sell we package everything and we
put it together and upload it to this
site and we can blank out the change log
and say wow we start out on a blank
sheet now everything is released
everything is fine this feels great
that's a awesome feeling to just you
know ship it and ah that's it i so enjoy
that moment when when everything feels
fresh and new and
and everyone can upgrade to the latest
and greatest
that moment is awesome
and as you said
pretty much until someone reports a bug
in the new version as well or a new one
or something bad or
anyway it's still a great feeling and
when we have done a new release we
always do releases on wednesdays so we
do releases on wednesdays and then
another one eight weeks later so when we
have done a release on a wednesday we
wait until the following monday to open
the feature window again
pretty much to give it a few days for
anyone to report alarming bugs because
if there's an alarming bug we don't open
the feature window and we work on the
emergency fixes that and maybe we do
another release
the next week or so
but if we open the feature window again
after that release we
pretty much allow features to get merged
and then it of course becomes the
question follows the question what
features do we merge
when we have the feature open and
it's a bit of a
random thing it's pretty much what
people are providing in pull requests
and that are in good shape mature and we
agree that it's good change
and
combined with someone who's actually
also able to review it and accept it and
you know work with the
author to make sure that it gets
up to
snuff and being good enough to merge
i usually myself have a few things that
i sort of
keep working on that i want to have
merged myself so i try to make sure that
i have pull requests ready or
in time because
i of course also sort of submit to the
same rules i'm only merging changes
during this
when the feature window is open that's
the only
time i can merge features as well
so i and of course i have a slightly
easier chance to get my stuff merged
because i know better than most exactly
how to do it and how to
do everything correctly and and have it
accepted by everyone
but otherwise it's uh it's a discussion
i usually allow anyone to provide
whatever and as long as you can motivate
it and discuss or argue for your sake
and for your features we discuss it and
we work with it and we make sure that we
we have some kind of rough consensus and
then go forward with that is it usually
a case where
it's a pull request through github and
they've done the feature and they just
want to see it be part of the library or
the curl project or
do they request that you guys could put
it into your schedule to do it i think
we have we have everything from the from
both
ways where all sort of and everything
there in between
some sometimes someone you know shows up
with a huge pull request and says i've
already done this we've used it for two
years here's the pull request and
sometimes it's just people you know
nagging and saying why don't you ever do
this feature we really need it
or something like that and
we have everything there and in between
of course the best thing is when someone
is actually working with us
the best thing is when people don't come
there and submit a really big one
the first thing we hear about it is when
they submit a few thousand lines of
diffs
because maybe they did it in a way we
don't quite agree with maybe they did it
in a way
we could have done better to take
advantage of whatever so it's better to
get that communication started early and
see
if we want to do this what's the best
way to do it and then work with with the
team to get it done
but i also get a lot of good ideas from
people who you know anyone who's
randomly using curls and says why oh i
thought of a good idea maybe it should
do this
and of course good ideas need to be
provided first because before we can do
anything like that right so a good idea
is a good idea even if sometimes good
ideas is also you know it's a little bit
too easy to just submit a good idea
because an idea is easy also but maybe
they're
actually implementing the idea is not
always as easy
and in addition to that
i work on curve full time i work for
wolf ssl and this
works because i sell curl support so
someone is paying me to help them with
use curl or
help them do curl correctly in their
applications and devices
and part of that they can also pay me to
help them get features done in curl that
they want and of course that has to be
featured that i accept and want into the
project as well so sometimes
people are actually
paying or i do work as part of my paid
contracts to land features as well
and have you ever had to say no that
doesn't work we don't want your money or
yes but it usually doesn't really work
like
it's rarely you know they say something
a and i say
i blankly say no if they say i want this
and i i think it's a bad
match for curl maybe we don't have to do
exactly like you asked maybe we could do
this parting curl and you should do that
part in your application and we could
work it through so it's rarely
yes and no situation is more of a gray
area where we can discuss exactly what
should curl do what should your
application do what shouldn't
so it's
it's more of a matter of
discussing and debating oftentimes when
i talk to people who actually pay for
this
and and it goes with
whoever submits a pull request too right
sometimes people submit a lot of things
that
maybe you were asking curl or lip curl
to do a little bit too much maybe you
should you know take away a little bit
and do that yourself outside of carl
instead or maybe this is completely out
of
what that curse shouldn't do
but having worked with the project for
so long we have to make a really big
effort to limit the number of features
and limit the growth so just you know
scaling everywhere we can't do that
because we have to make sure that we
stick to the concept here and not
just branch off in every imaginable
direction so if a listener had a
an idea or
an improvement or something how would
you recommend they reach out generally
the best way to discuss anything is on
the mailing lists we're an old open
source project we use mailing lists so
that's the best way to discuss
ideas if you're just having an idea if
maybe you have an embryo or a start of
some code actually you started to do
something a change or reading a concept
written a concept
then maybe you could submit a pull
request and here's my first shot take a
look at this would this be acceptable to
you and then work with us maybe within
that pull request this is a good base
maybe you should do it like this instead
maybe this contradicts what we're doing
here we should you know remodel and do
it like that and so on and just be
prepared to
work with us and do a little bit of back
and forth and go forward
usually i also try to make sure that
if you really want to see something
happen
make sure that you also stick around for
the follow-up discussion because don't
just throw code at us and go away and
come back in two weeks because if you do
you'll find those questions or follow-up
questions that were filed
30 minutes after your pull request was
made and then it's been dead silent for
two weeks
so if you really want to make something
happen be there and make sure that you
follow code style and you make sure that
everything works you have test cases you
have
you document the new features and stuff
like that and just make sure that
everything is in shape then you have i
would say
it isn't hard to do anything to do
changes in curl as long as you just do
things correctly and you have some
patience and stick around
thank you that brings us into the last
section of the show
a strange one but if you were starting
carl again today
would you
we did you all the same or you know
hindsight's a wonderful thing and we
should maybe indulge at some point in
our lives
yeah i would imagine that if i hadn't
started it i it feels like something
i wouldn't start now but
if i hadn't done curl or lip girl
someone else would have done it and then
there would exist something else that
would be similar to curl i mean as you
described me from the beginning i like
internet transfer internet protocols
that's sort of i'm intrigued by that i'm
fascinated i think that's fun and i
i mean i participate in a few different
open source projects and i do some other
things and i so apart from curl for
example the biggest ones i think that i
maintain as well is liebus h2 and ca-ris
projects they do ssh and dns
stuff so that's sort of the area i'm
interested in internet protocols
internet transfers so if i hadn't done
curl if i didn't work so much on curl
today i would probably sort of
still be nosing around and digging
around in network related libraries
network related code
so maybe not
curl specifically but i would have done
something internet-ish
at least
what advice can you give
after your hard-earned experience
for other open source project founders
or those that wish to help with a
project like carl well for other
maintainers i don't know i don't want to
say that others should do what i've done
or i don't think i've done anything
magically
strange or or wonderful in the code
project i try to
lead by example i try to listen in what
other people say i try to make sure that
others can do as much as possible so
that i don't have to do things make sure
that we can widen the number of
developers and everyone can do things
individually and independently so that
we don't
introduce unnecessary bottlenecks in the
project i'm not sure i've succeeded in
that very good
but
that's what i'm trying to do we're open
for discussions and ideas and
suggestions and stuff like that but i
think all of this is just how to
how any open source maintainer would
think and consider
open source working on pursuers is a lot
of
working with people so of course yeah
you just have to realize that there's a
lot of different people and you need to
understand that people are different
there are many different cultures you
have to have a thick skin and manage
people
somehow that's really hard
and usually when i try to give advice to
anyone who wants to participate in the
project or you know join in and do
something here with us
i try to
get people to work with something that
you think is
fun or or that concerns you maybe you
have an itch that's to scratch maybe you
have a use case you you haven't
found fulfilled or you found a typo you
want to fix or something that actually
concerns you because it's much more fun
to work on something that affects you
personally so maybe that little feature
you're missing or that little thing that
doesn't work the way you want it
get to that and fix that work on that
and that doesn't
only matter i mean that's only not a
curl recommendation that's whatever you
want to do in open source it's much
better if you start with something that
is near to your heart
otherwise i'm not a guy to give advice
i feel more like a lottery winner so do
you have any advice on what lottery
numbers to pick no i don't it was
fortunate for me i'm not sure i'm the
one to tell anyone how to repeat it well
i think we'll accept that but i feel
you're downplaying your role
dramatically well
maybe but it's really hard for me to say
what what works for me and what what
doesn't work for me i'm trying to
run and be in the project the way i
would have appreciated someone else to
do it if i was a participant in the
project sort of
yeah that comes across i mean your
personal applies to emails and things
and
how you can induct stuff it is a really
good example
so
what are some of the things that most
users don't know about maintaining like
a project like carl
we've talked about the support requests
you get in but is there anything else
that
goes on behind the scenes that is not
normal for open source project
if you're an open source maintainer for
us
as a smaller project because i think
curl is still a smaller project it might
be well used and popular and known but
it's still a smaller project in that
i'm the only one working on it full time
so i think what a lot of people
not if you're an open source mate i'm
the only one working on it full-time
so i think what a lot of people
not if you're an open source maintainer
you know this but people from the
outside you know if people who are
working with other things
don't realize how much
other things than working on code you
have to do when you're maintaining a
project you know maintaining the servers
maintaining the mailing list doing
releases
setting up your
scripts to update things to do
the ci jobs the
everything else around the project that
needs to be maintained for it to run
smoothly
i think a lot of people are
sort of missing that huge amount of work
that you have to keep up in a project to
just keep everything
afloat and going forward smoothly so i
think sometimes i spend a lot of time on
stuff like that you know just polishing
things around the project to make sure
that it goes forward well but
that work
isn't visible at all because when
everything works you know you don't see
what work that went on to make sure that
nothing broke
the other day for example
in a weak moment i upgraded a little
detail in my
server and the server that runs all the
mailing lists and in that little
moment of bad
decisions i accidentally upgraded my
python insulation on the server to no
longer feature python
2 and then in one blow i just broke a
lot of server infrastructure so the
mailing lists and i run a lot of mailing
lists they all broke in one moment so
and then i had to spend several days
restoring
a python 2
installation so that the mailing list
could work again and of course from the
outside
it wasn't really okay the breakage was
possibly visible for a select few who
tried to use the email in the mailing
list i i didn't actually see that
but it was still you know a lot of work
just to bring up everything back to look
exactly like you did before and for me i
bet i spent 12 hours on that or maybe
more and it was a really
annoying and tough time here but yeah
you know
from the outside i didn't do anything on
curl everything was just looking the
same way as it did before it wasn't on a
friday evening after a glass of wine was
it i i think it was actually worse but
it wasn't friday evening but it was
still you know i it was one of those
decisions i did without even considering
and then afterwards like oh what did i
do
you know oops this was not good
then i had to suffer through it
yeah so that's a very good example right
i'm going to close off a section and
then start wrapping up but i know one of
the statistics that you like to talk
about is a number of command line
arguments that you can do i think it's
750 or something what are some of the
weird bizarre unknown ones that you
would like to let somebody know about
i actually added the 245th
the other day oh wow so 245
and the most recent one is
but it's not in a release yet but it's
dash dash json yeah there's been a bit
of noise about that one hasn't there
yeah exactly there's been a bit
positive and negatives about it but this
is a very simple one i've added it to
make it simpler for people to send and
receive json and i think a lot of people
have been
pretty positive about it so that that
will be fun now i think some of my
favorite ones that might not be that
well used always one of my absolute
favorite ones is the dash dash lib curl
which is a command line option that
converts
the
command line to a lib curl code or
generates a template code in c
for the command line you wrote basically
if you write a command line using curl
you do some kind of transfer upload
download whatever and then you think i
want to convert this into an application
instead that uses slip curl
you run the same command line and you do
leave curl example.c and then it'll
generate that example.c for you with a
skeleton code that uses slip curl to do
it that exact same
i really wish i knew about that one
i just did that the other day i think i
was on the mail list but i'll do that
and check things out
yeah i think it's really cool it's not
complete of course because
it's hard to convert all of that into c
code exactly but you get a pretty good
start to base your further work on
whatever you want to do when you want to
do a lip card application and what is
good is that most bindings for lib curl
are are actually rather thin so most
bindings philip curl have the same
options and stuff like that so you can
usually fairly easily even convert that
c code into for example php code or
python code or other bindings that are
because they usually
look fairly similar to lip curl itself
that's one of my favorites another one
that i
like to point out to people is the dash
dash resolve function
which is a way to
pretty much
populate the dns cache from the command
line so you can add an ip address for a
host name
on the command line
which is the way basically what you want
to do is if you for example if you type
curl
example.com
but you decided to host that example.com
on your local machine for example on
localhost
and then you get a you know you get
problems with the name because the
certificate maybe won't match stuff like
that
so then you have an option for curl that
you can say that
in this invocation example.com is going
to use this particular ip address
instead
that's brilliant because that's normally
something difficult to do when you're
running ci jobs or editing et cetera
hosts and everything like that
exactly or when you're experimenting or
you want to send in a particular name on
that particular ip address and stuff
like that so
resolve
resolve yeah i'm writing that down thank
you
excellent so i'm going to wrap up now
obviously carl is a very powerful tool
with a strong history and global
deployment base but if there's one thing
that a software engineer should remember
from our show what would you like it to
be
i usually maintain that one of the
primary qualities that made
curl has made curl and lip crear succeed
is just persistence to just keep on
working on it until it actually works
and until actually succeeds
i often get to hear from people who try
out things to you know write the tool
and then say that well nobody's using it
it doesn't work or nobody is succeeding
and i usually then try to go back and
see that it took me many many many years
with curl and lip curl until we had
a number of users so
i think
if
the one
particular criteria to actually succeed
with something like this is to just
give it enough time and effort so if you
just want to and just keep on working on
it you can succeed
in the long run it's not
necessarily
an immediate hit just because it's a
good idea you just sometimes have to
keep at it
and there was there anything we missed
that you'd like to talk about or mention
i could mention that we just recently
surpassed 1 000 commit authors in the
project so we're more than 1 000 people
who have actually written code merged
into the project
sometimes people think of
me as so yeah i'm the lead developer but
we're also a huge amount of people who
actually contributed code to it
more other names
[Laughter]
well we have the thanks list in git and
that the thanks also includes all
contributors who
that's also people who have reported
bugs and helped out in other ways and
that's i think that's approaching 2600
names now so quite a lot of people are
helping out all the time that's
brilliant
where can people find out more or get in
touch
everything curl is of course on curl
curl.se
if you want to read up on carl we have
this book on everything.curl.dev
which is my book efforts to document
curl and everything about me is on
daniel.hacks.sc and now of course i'm on
twitter as bag there and i i tweet a lot
of curl stuff
non-stop
a lot of blabbing daniel thank you for
coming on the show it's been a real
pleasure this is gavin henry for
software engineering radio thank you for
listening
thanks for listening to sc radio an
educational program brought to you by
ieee software magazine for more about
the podcast including other episodes
visit our website at se radio.net
to provide feedback you can comment on
each episode on the website or reach us
on linkedin facebook twitter or through
our slack channel at scradio.slack.com
you can also email us at team
sc-radio.net
this and all other episodes of se radio
is licensed under creative commons
license 2.5
thanks for listening